welcome to meditating with John Harvey
key I'm a cognitive psychologist and a
cognitive scientist at the University of
Toronto I I study scientifically and
academically mindfulness and related
phenomena like flow insight mystical
experience and wisdom I've also been
practicing the past of meditation for 29
years contemplation for 29 years in Tai
Chi Chuan for 29 years I've been
teaching them professionally for close
to 20 years this is actually a course
and on Mondays and Thursdays I actually
teach a progressive settles and
practices in order to gain engage in a
deep mindfulness training and
transformation on Tuesdays Wednesdays
Fridays and Saturdays we just meet and
sit at the end of every session there is
a question and answer period if you're
just joining us you're welcome to study
today we'll just be sitting but I
recommend you go back and look at day
one day three and yesterday's videos
because those are the three teaching
videos that you missed so far finding
your Center
finding your root and finding your flow
more general announcements for this week
we're going to stay with the Monday and
Thursday teaching schedule there's a
possibility there's a possibility
Mondays and Fridays this is not settled
yet but just a heads up in case we do
end up shifting it all so I've been
working with Christopher master Pietro
revising the meditation manual that I
have written that is based on the course
that I'm teaching you I was speaking
with him last night and we're expecting
to have the complete revision done in
June and the meditation manual will be
to see who will be seeking publication
at that point so there is a meditation
manual a book for this course that will
coming out hopefully later this year
because the last time we reviewed
finding your flow there's you know
training your attention by putting it
into a state where you're really putting
significant demand and challenge on it
well really increasing your
interoception by expanding your
awareness across your abdomen and into
your abdomen then enriching it by
noticing the detail differences so
you're zooming out and zooming in at the
same time getting that optimal gripping
that we talked about you do that here
you do that at the heart and each place
you use the motion of your breath to
anchor your attention and then you do
the finding a flow here here shoulders
back torso until you're following the
whole of your breath with the whole of
the torso your focal awareness is here
your peripheral awareness is here it's
really deeply enhances and integrates
your interception with your
introspection which really increases
your mind site this is a seagull's term
for your ability to pick up on other
people's mental states and your own
mental states which is one of the things
you're seeking to Train through training
mindfulness and it really grounds you
more and more in the living presence of
the body okay so everybody get ready
we'll begin when I say the word forgive
make sure you're in a comfortable
posture always take time to Center and
real take as much time as you need find
your flow please remember please
remember when you're finding your flow
don't hyperventilate though it might
prevent delight okay everyone please
begin
you
slowly begin to come out of your
practice trying as best you can to
integrate what you've cultivated in your
practice with your everyday cognition
open your eyes trying to keep that same
state of mind and body looking around
the room reconnecting to
it's a fuse to your background all right
we'll take any questions people might
have right now are there any questions
Omar all right so it looks like we're
just going to wait a minute to see if
there's any questions and Mars doing a
final search as always I'm very grateful
for the fantastic help I get from amar
and from my son Jason just wait a couple
more minutes to see if there's any
last-minute questions here's a question
if you lose the flow should you just go
through these points again you'll tend
to lose the flow in general because
you're beginning to learn I would
recommend just doing a very brief
reconnecting with the Dante abdomen area
the heart the shoulders the body just
try and get that reengaged of the whole
thing but get back to the breath sort of
as quickly as as you can what do we
think about using audio aids this is
from Marc in meditation I use this all
the time myself
the difficulty with audio aids it's
called encoding specificity this is from
cognitive science your brain is always
storing the context in addition to what
information it's storing and you can use
this to your advantage if you want to
remember something for an exam you know
our tests play some music while you're
studying that material then imagine the
music when you are studying it but the
reverse is also the case that also
limits you so what's going to happen
with audio aids especially things like
music is your brain is going to do
encoding specificity and it's going to
always be looking for that when you're
trying to get into the mindfulness State
which means when you are places where
you can't you
those aids in meditation or more much
more importantly when you're trying to
bring mindfulness into your everyday
life you won't have those aids available
and you'll your brain will find it
difficult to transition into the
mindfulness you need so I would
recommend as soon as you can gradually
because you probably have built up a
habit weaning yourself off of any of
those kinds of auditory aids the next
one is from Andre Ferrer in the first
video you said about getting to feel
your pulse in the thumb how do I do that
without pinching it too hard yeah you
have to sort of move it around and play
with it
it takes quite a bit of practice and
sensitivity to get it so you try it I
recommend trying doing it outside of
meditation just you know you're sitting
down I hope you'll creep who who's
happier your happen to be sort of
quarantined with but anyways you know
just sit and practice moving around
trying to find your pulse outside of
meditation without having to pinch
really hard and eventually you will find
it it's a bit of a nap it's a bit of a
nap for some people other people can
just do it right away my I myself had to
play with it quite a bit before I could
find it this is from Nicklaus am I
supposed to envision actual roots coming
from my body into the ground yes
initially sort of envisioned this is
using imagination in an imaginal sense
not just an imaginary sense using
imagination to train perception do that
initially until that sense becomes
readily available to to you and then you
can let the image go we're going to talk
about this throughout the course you
know you're engaging them in some inner
speech right now which is different from
your monkey mind and your because it's
directed you're in out or you might be
note you might be labeling well that's
inner speech that's directed it's also
directed imagination these are like the
wrath that the Buddha talks about these
are inner coaching you have to do this
until eventually you get the skill that
you don't need to talk to yourself in
order to do it I can walk across this
room and I don't have to talk to myself
in order to say lift my right leg lift
my left leg I can catch a ball I don't
this talk to myself I can do Tai Chi
Chuan
without having to
to myself but what I was learning I had
to sort of talk to myself I had to use
imagination in fact that I cheat manuals
recommend that but eventually that will
fall away and you will directly be able
to do the practice Holly I'm having a
hard time not hyperventilating the flow
me because I have thought not to
hyperventilate top of my mind do you
have any suggestions maybe leave the
flow practice away for a couple of days
just to the center of routing and going
into the meditation and then wouldn't
come back try and do it very light touch
no you're not going to try and get too
much of a flow just a little bit of flow
in the abdomen chest shoulders right so
leave it off go back to the centering
and rooting and then gradually work your
way back in to the practice if I start
to slow to this because I have not
rooted properly it can be this is from
Diane it could also be that you're
starting to fall asleep Diane so make
sure that your head isn't rocking
forward initially because the slouch may
begin with you doing this so you can
tell you're falling asleep if it feels
like sort of your mind is the scope of
your - collapse and it's getting fuzzy
it's getting sort of warm and
comfortable and that's a that's a sign
that what you need to do a little bit
more flow make sure your baby breathing
getting enough oxygen into your into
your practice I strongly recommend that
many of you consider taking up I
recommended this yesterday I'm moving
mindfulness practice like pi Chi Chuan
or yoga because right before you sit
because that will help actually energize
you while getting you properly routed
and flowing so that you will not tend to
slouch or fall asleep when you're
sitting and again when I'm centered and
rooted all I feel and I focus on my
breathing I feel like losing
consciousness like following to sleep my
head is not tilted forward anything is
this is this normal it can be because
what's typically happening as I
mentioned your brain is getting very
powerful signals that your to
interception awareness and you're
relaxing and it can miss read those
single those signals as falling asleep
so just reengage maybe even your breath
a little bit
you know we engage flow a little bit
more but also like I said you may want
to take some kind of moving mindfulness
practice that you can engage just before
you sit because that will help energize
you in the appropriate manner
this is Alexei how long do you
personally do rooting for I do not quite
understand it and doing it makes me
takes me further for my state so I feel
if I don't do it or do it briefly my
practice is better you may be able to do
it briefly I don't know you individually
this is one of the difficulties with the
virtual teaching if you feel that you
are finding your route and could do it
very briefly then that's fine
do that as long as you've got that sense
of sensitivity on stability that you
could preserve well you're finding your
flow then you're fine all right so I
want to thank everybody for joining I
want to thank always Omar and Jason for
helping me out as they do please
subscribe to this channel to be notified
of the next video and any changes we
might need to make to the shed but we're
going to talk we're going to keep doing
30 except Sundays we'll always have two
teaching days they'll always be Q&A the
video channel will have lots of other
videos that I think you will find
relevant to both responding to a current
situation and to the long-term project
of cultivating transformation and wisdom
and so I hope that you all continue to
sit remember that continuity of practice
is more important than quantity and I
look forward to sitting with you all
tomorrow morning thank you for your time
and attention
take good care
see you tomorrow